It's 9/36 and time for staff breakfast from B&B Pharmacy with Warren Hasse.
Well many people say that flying is not as dangerous as driving an automobile.
Others say you never get me up one of those things.
And then others say well I'd like to go to the moon and others say never.
So it doesn't matter how you look at it, everybody's got a different opinion about aviation.
Personally we think it's the greatest thing since sliced bread really.
But this morning a gentleman who is interested in aviation
and makes a living worrying about the possibilities of aircraft accidents
and a very responsible role in that regard is our guest on staff breakfast.
He's here visiting friends and relatives, Mr. Bobby Ray Allen.
Bobby Ray, good to have you with us this morning.
Thank you very much, good to be here.
And let me first, let's run through that long title that you have once again, which is what?
The title is Special Assistant to the Director of the Bureau of Aviation Safety
of the National Transportation Safety Board.
Well other than that, we just about have time for the closing conversion.
Not that we got that in.
Which sounds like it does have a great deal to do with aviation safety, is that right?
Yes, the board is the agency established by Congress
to investigate all aircraft accidents throughout the United States
and attempt to determine probable cause and prevent the recurrence of aircraft accidents.
And you're not here in any official capacity right now?
No, we're visiting relatives here.
I have two very favorite uncles living in the area, Mr. Marion Brown and Mr. Edgar Brown.
Well I just checked him out and he knows what he's talking about.
I showed him an aircraft accident which I was in a few years ago
and he took a look at the picture and said it looks like this is what happened
and you're absolutely right, that's what did happen.
He had it figured out very well.
What is this percentage of aircraft safety versus automobile safety?
Could you give us any idea on that? What's your thinking?
Well it's very difficult to make a valid comparison.
In many respects there is no valid comparison.
But on the highways each year there are slightly over 50,000 people killed
and in aviation in the United States there are approximately 1200 killed each year.
In commercial aviation there will be something on the order of 250 to 300 average
and in private aviation there will be approximately 1000 fatalities a year.
And of course the auto industry or the various departments of public safety
I think base their ratio on a per mile driven ratio.
Do you figure yours on an airline mileage ratio of any chance?
There's been a lot of controversy on the yardstick for establishing it right over the past several years.
One group would use aircraft hours flown.
Another group would use the yardstick of passenger miles flown.
And I suppose that I prefer to use the aircraft hours flown
or in better yet one mission, one take off the landing
or take off your en route cruise to your destination and landing.
Because it'd be from here to Amral or here to Los Angeles regardless of distance.
Why do you say that? What's your thinking on that?
Well I think the greatest amount of exposure occurs during take off or landing.
And if you're going to be actually any time you attempt to establish an accident rate
or a fatality rate in any mode of transportation you have to take into consideration the exposure.
And the greatest exposure occurs during take off or during landing.
And that's the reason that I would like to see a rate based on each mission or each flight
rather than just passenger miles flown.
Then you're saying that there's not a great deal of possibility of midair crashes.
Of course it exists but the possibility is fairly remote is it not?
Well, I started speech one time and said that we had the potential or the problem of midair collisions
ever since Will returned to Orville and said let's build another one.
I think that right now the midair collision problem is being discussed throughout the entire United States.
I think that it can't help but, the problem can't help but increase because our civil aviation fleet
is projected to increase to approximately 260,000 airplanes in the next 10 years.
Now that's doubling the fleet that we have today.
Right now we have approximately 120,000 to 130,000 airplanes in the civil aviation fleet.
And out of this 130,000 aircraft approximately 27 to 2800 are involved in commercial aviation.
Now by the year 1980 they expect the civil aviation fleet to increase to approximately 260,000 airplanes.
But the commercial transport fleet will only increase to about 3100 airplanes.
But the size of those, the loads that they can carry will be much greater, will they not?
Yes, the Q7-47 that's, well, let's just enjoy it.
It's made in flight here about two months ago and in Seattle, Washington is capable of carrying about 500 passengers.
Unbelievable. Unbelievable.
I couldn't believe it last December our band and choir here at PAM high school had the privilege of performing.
Well actually I'm national television on both coasts at football games.
But they flew to New York in an airliner that seated at that time to carry 250 passengers.
I didn't think there was anything that big, but there was.
It's huge. I can't even start to visualize when I'll carry 500.
The Lockheed aircraft is building a new jetliner called the Kim 11, I believe it is.
And the passenger carrying capacity of that aircraft will be about 350.
This is one they refer to as the Airbus.
An interesting comparison on the 747, if you land 3 747s with a full passenger load at an airport,
it would be almost the same as disembarking the passengers on the Queen Mary.
So this will give you some feel for the impact the 747 is going to have on your airports around the country.
That's tremendous. I imagine there's an area that a lot of people are not familiar with and don't understand how it's accomplished.
We might discuss this business of routes and altitudes and so on and so forth.
Your automobiles today on our super highways, Interstate 40, for instance, is divided.
One and two lanes go in one direction and there's a divider between and two lanes going the other direction.
You have somewhat similar or comparable flying rules and regulations, do you not, for east and west traffic and so on?
Yes, there again. Actually, I suppose you'd say there are two sets of rules.
You have a set of rules that prevail when the weather is good, no instrument conditions.
And then you have the rules that exist under instrument weather conditions.
And under your IFR or instrument rules, altitude and traffic control is accomplished with their traffic control system.
And under the visual flight rules or IFR conditions, the traffic flow is pretty much left in the cockpit of the aircraft subject to the rules that exist.
These rules are that if you're flying north or south, you will fly at an odd or even a thousand foot plus or minus 500 feet.
And east and west, I believe the rule is called the quadrennial rule. And then the responsibility for maintaining a lookout for other aircraft rests in the cockpit.
There's a tremendous amount of assistance that would be available to the pilots from the FAA air traffic control system.
But the pilot has to avail himself from this.
In your job, do you personally go out on the scene of aircraft accidents for investigation or do you send teams out or is that at all in the area of your position?
Yes, I have not personally investigated an accident for several years. I started out with the board as a field investigator working out of the Chicago office.
But on a air carrier accident or a catastrophic accident involving passengers, we usually dispatch a team from Washington D.C. that's comprised of specialists in various areas.
Power plants, systems, human factors, operations, engineering, flight recorder, readout.
And each individual is responsible for a particular phase of the investigation.
Now on a general aviation accident investigation, this is generally investigated by two people, two men.
As I mentioned earlier, the large team type investigation in the team, in some instances, is comprised of 40 to 50 people. And this is primarily the difference.
Speaking of something like the collision over Grand Canyon, that's where your big teams go out and work on it.
Historically, over the past 10 years, we've had on the order of about 12 what we call team type investigations a year.
It'll run anywhere from 8 to 14 major catastrophic accidents a year. And that number has remained fairly static since about 1955 or '56.
Well really, any time you have an airplane accident, it's an amount to be in catastrophic, I guess, at least certainly in commercial aviation.
There's no question because there's always a large number of board and it's a big airplane.
You take a little small airplane, monier, piper, patchy, something like that, where you've only got one or two passengers.
It's just like an automobile accident where it takes one or two lives.
You have to be very careful when you talk about a catastrophic accident. It's a matter of personal concern and involvement.
I recall I was in an accident one time and as far as I was concerned, I was the only one aboard the aircraft and it was catastrophic.
Surely, absolutely. I'm saying it's true. It was an automobile accident, I believe that's certainly true.
You've also had another big responsibility. You were on an American United States team which was working with the Russians concerning the airline, commercial airline, between New York and Moscow.
And I think that'd be interesting to find out how that worked out, what some of the problems were that you had to overcome.
And I'd like to discuss that with you right after we pause for these words.
Our guest is Bobby Ray Allen, gentlemen who's here visiting relatives in half-accidents for the government.
And I'm interested, Bobby, let's talk about this situation between Russia and the United States and the commercial lines that were open between Moscow and New York.
There were lots of problems to be worked out there where they're not.
Yes, the original negotiation that the Russians established commercial esters between New York and Moscow started back in 1960. And you may recall that in 1961 there was a rogue international affair called the Berlin Crisis.
And our negotiation with that time broke down. As a matter of fact, my personal life was interrupted at that time. I was recalled in Navy.
And then the negotiations were resumed in 1966. The basic agreement had been signed back in 1960. But the details of how the air service would be implemented had not been worked out.
And so in 1966 President Johnson started the negotiations off again.
And the recent negotiations consisted of two meetings. One that would be held in Moscow and the U.S. contingent would travel to Moscow.
And then the second phase of the negotiations would be the meeting in New York City where the Russian delegation would travel to the United States.
Our group consisted of about 20 people. And it covered just one phase of the negotiations with facilities to navigational facilities to certification.
In my particular area of responsibility was to establish the ground rules for the investigation of an accident and the unlikely event of one should occur.
And we traveled to Moscow in January of 1967 and remained there for a period of about six weeks.
And during that period we were given permission to invest here to expand and look at the facilities at Timoshibo Airport here in Moscow. And then we looked at the ultimate airport located up at Victory.
And I was somewhat surprised when I expected that the Russians would not permit us to go into the radar room.
And a lot of the facilities there they might be somewhat reluctant to let us look.
But much to my surprise when we arrived here they let us have a very cooperative approach. We expected the what would be equivalent of our air traffic control center.
Looked at their radar installations. And once they had told us that we could go into the radar room I had expected that they would turn the radar to stand by or turn it off.
And as we walked in the suite was operating. Very impressive. I was very much impressed with the technical know-how and ability of the Russian people.
Are we comparable in that respect? Or could you make any kind of estimate?
I don't really think that I could make a comparison primarily because I think you have to realize that what I saw was probably the best that they had to offer as far as commercial air service was concerned.
We did not travel into some of their factories or some of the other facilities that would give you an opportunity to make a valid comparison.
I guess maybe based on personal projection that I'm convinced that they surpassed us. But certainly they don't want to give up some of their accomplishments.
As for instance some of the things that you worked out I assume let's suppose that a Russian airliner crashes that's bound for the United States crashes in Russia.
Will a Russian team investigate? Those are the kind of things that you had to work out and if an American plane were to crash in Russia who would investigate?
Would it be a joint team? Are those the problems that came up?
Yes, let me see if I can clarify this a little more. There's an organization in Montreal called the International Civil Aviation Organization. Now there are approximately 109 countries throughout the world that belong to that particular organization.
Now by membership in that organization and by agreeing to abide by the rules that have been established by the International Civil Aviation Organization it's not necessary to negotiate a bilateral agreement with the member countries.
Unfortunately Russia back in 1944 decided not to join the International Civil Aviation Organization. Consequently it became necessary for us to negotiate each facet of this air service on an individual basis.
And what we did was we arrived in an agreement with the Russians that we would abide by most of the provisions of annex 13 to the Chicago Convention or the IKO manuals.
And in the case of an American aircraft crashing in Russia, the Russian would investigate the accident as the state of occurrence and we would be permitted to participate with the Russians in the investigation as the state of registry and as the state of manufacture.
And if a Russian aircraft crashed in the United States it would work exactly the same way.
So those are the things that have to be worked out. It's good that you've gotten the work done. I think there's no problems now hopefully and we hope nothing ever happens.
I hope we never have to use this.
Bobby you I would assume would be an avid reader of aviation or aircraft books stories about flying the latest big hit airport had to be of interest to you I'm sure.
Yes.
What was that one where this airliner and this military jet were on a crash course, collision course. Can't think of the name of that one. Do you remember that book?
Oh that was a book that was written by Ernest Gayan and you caught me short here. I can't think of the title of it either but it was an exciting one, an exciting movie.
A Long High and the Mighty. Was that it? No.
No that was B-17 story.
That's right.
You're correct. It was an Ernest Gayan book.
But it's an area in which I assume with the success that we've had of several of these that we will have many more fine novels written. Actually, since you mentioned Orville and Wilbur, I believe we're just barely into the crawling stage of aviation.
It's rather interesting when you consider that the first flight at Kitty Hawk occurred on December the 17th in 1903. That's only 66 years ago and we've gone from their first flight in the old bywing airplane that they built there to 747 and fuselage of the 747 is longer than the total distance of their first flight.
Amazing. Amazing. Bobby, all you people are in the aviation industry and you've been in it, you've studied it and know it forward and backward pretty much I would assume.
And you get around in bold sessions. You've been able to sit here through moon missions, these various launches that we've had. I imagine a lot of people say, "Man, I wish I was on that."
And the next one says, "Not me." Or do they? Would everybody that's involved in your work like to be on one of those jaunts to the moon?
A few years ago, I probably would have given my teeth ago. I'd think about it a little while now, I guess.
And now it's proven that it can be done and before it wasn't. You'd rather have gone before you were convinced. It still sounds exciting though. And aviation, that field certainly is and it's growing.
The statistics that you passed on to us earlier about the growth and private aviation and commercial aviation are fantastic.
The communities such as ours right here in Tampa realizing the necessity of better airfields, better aviation facilities.
And we're over time here, Bobby. I want to go back to one thing that passed through my mind. We were talking about these air corridors and you mentioned the instrument flights.
In many, many, many times you come down into a city, especially up in the east, I guess, where you've got more bad weather than we do here, where you land by instrument.
And then you come down through clouds from 10,000 and then break out at 700 feet or something like that. To those who have never done it or have only done it once or twice, it's quite a thrill. How safe are we under those conditions?
I think the instrument landing system that we have, if you have a full instrument landing facility at an airport, there's no major in it at all.
The rut is highly perfected and the equipment is very reliable.
It certainly is. It's amazing. These boys will come out and there they are right on, you can see the end of the runway down there a quarter of a mile or a half mile away and they're in perfect alignment.
It's truly amazing and more work is being done constantly to further assure the safety of passengers as it must.
Bobby, our thanks to you so much for coming down and being with us on staff breakfast this morning. It's been very interesting bringing out these points about flying. Let me ask us, where's home for you?
Well, home presently is in Fort Worth. I was originally born in Winsborough, Texas and grew up in Marshall, Texas.
And I was going to ask, being that close though, I guess you drove out here and you didn't fly. Good. Thank you very much, Bobby Ray Allen for being with us on staff breakfast this morning.